So, we often uh
we often speak about uh in um
and it's often mentioned in our talks,
things like um
that one should frequently recollect,
you know, like what the suttas talk
about. That um you should keep trying to
That um you should keep trying to
understand, frequently recollect on
things, um
discern the context of your actions, uh
uncover the intentions behind your
actions, and so on.
So, it's um
it's obviously it's it's like a it's a
it's a it's a form of practice. There's
um there's quite a lot to be done.
Um and actually all of that, as we
as we explained probably number of times
before, all of that
all of that
is what the actual
uh
right meditation is or should be.
Because when you reflect on things,
when you're trying to get, you know, to
the bottom of something, so to speak, um
you cannot do that mechanically. I mean,
you can try, but then um
if there is no self-awareness of that
process, it's um it's not really going
to lead to anything.
It's just going to become a dry kind of
uh repetitive mantra or recitation, and
so on.
So, it's like
the the the the main property of the
correct meditation would be that
self-awareness of your thinking.
>> [snorts]
>> So, it's not about trying to get rid of
what you think,
what you're thinking. It's not about
indulging what the mind pressures you,
what citta pressures you to think.
Um it's about finding a balance between
the two, uh through being aware of what
thoughts are present, and so on. So,
obviously that that has like many, many
that that has like many, many
um
layers of development, so to speak. But,
it's it's kind of understandable that
that people, especially in the
beginning, need something more palpable.
Because obviously
um your whole experience, everything is
geared towards sense objects, geared
towards uh that level of engagement.
Uh so then even when when when things
like uh reflection are heard about,
things about, you know, how you should
be uh rightly thinking about things,
reflecting, and uncovering,
that too will be approached in that same
okay, so what do I do specifically, you
know, tell me like cuz if I just say to
you, "Well, just reflect on things."
Uh for many people it could just sound
like too abstract, not not palpable
enough. So, it's like, "Yeah, but how do
I reflect on things? How do I
What do I do specifically in order to
fulfill the requirement of reflecting on
things?" And then they make it into
technique again, make it into a mindless
method. And um ironically, asking the question
And um ironically, asking the question
of "How do I reflect on things?"
is
closer to the right reflection than that
following the steps of reflection that
you heard about, the methods.
But without any self-awareness,
uh that won't be recognized.
So, people would then move move past it and
people would then move move past it and
fall onto again on something overly uh
defined that will not uh
uh encourage and maintain the the
self-awareness. And so it's like So, for example, like
And so it's like So, for example, like
you can't you can't help but feel
okay, I I I I I need to do something
about the practice. Like, you know, you
you come to our channel and then you
hear that all the
meditation techniques are wrong. So,
it's like people say, "Aha, so I
shouldn't be meditating."
So, in the past I used to sit every
morning and every evening to meditate.
But now I heard I learned that I
meditation is wrong, so I shouldn't be
sitting in the morning and the evening.
But um in other talks I said number of
times, "No, if you if you if you need a
structure, if you need a routine, if you
need something that will make you feel
like you're doing something about the
practice, you can continue sitting in the morning,
you can continue sitting in the morning,
in the evening, in the afternoon. You
can whatever.
Five times a day if you want.
Um the point is
not to whether you're sitting or not.
The point is what you're doing and what
you're expecting to come out of it. What
you're doing
during for the duration of your sitting
uh and what do you expect to come out of
it. So, are you just sitting as a sense of
So, are you just sitting as a sense of
like a calming duty or state of
mindlessness? And um or are you actually
And um or are you actually
uh making an active effort to to be
self-aware, um
um
cognizant of of uh whatever's presently
enduring and so on.
So, from that point of view, um like if
you are if you're practicing, say say if
you're keeping the precepts and training
in virtue,
and then you want to be doing something
more proactive, so to speak. Not that
keeping the precepts is not proactive,
but it might not feel like that in the
beginning. Um
Um
yeah, there's plenty you can do uh and
all of that will revolve around uh
rightly reflecting, correctly
reflecting. None of that will obviously
revolve around just uh
state of mindlessness and absorption in
your to sensation and stuff, but plenty
of our other talks cover that. So,
so it's like
if you need to do something,
say morning, evening, or whenever you
have a spare time, yeah,
sit down quietly,
half an hour, hour, whatever time you
have to spare,
and you want to be
basically practicing meditation through asking the
practicing meditation through asking the
right questions.
Asking the right questions that would
engage the mind,
that would result not in you being
self-aware only during your meditation
meditation quote and quote time,
but those those questions, those
contexts that those questions point at
wouldn't carry on throughout the day.
So, for example,
um at the end of
say at the end of every day,
you could set time aside,
um sit down, and simply
ask yourself, "Okay, so
for this like in this last
I don't know, 12 16 hours that I've been
awake, um
um
how did I spend my day?" So, again,
So, again,
it's not about finding the right answer
or providing the right answer, it's
about s- uh uh shedding light onto certain
s- uh uh shedding light onto certain
contexts through asking these questions.
So, "How did I spend my day?
"How did I spend my day?
How did I spend my time throughout the
day?" And see what's what's the first
thing that pops in your mind when you
think that.
"Oh, I spent it like this. I spent it
like that.
>> [gasps]
>> I was doing this. I was doing that."
"How do you feel about that?"
So, what would be the
the underlying overall feeling in regard
to the question of well, in regard to
the the the answer that popped up when you
the the answer that popped up when you
asked yourself, "How did I spend my
day?" Would it be like, "Oof, could have been
Would it be like, "Oof, could have been
better." So, I don't feel quite
quite okay or I'm I feel pleased. I feel
displeased. Um
Um
And then you can go even more
specifically. So,
"During this day,
last day, during my waking hours,
what did I choose to attend to
mostly?" So, throughout the day,
So, throughout the day,
>> [gasps]
>> um
"How often
did I choose to attend things on the
basis of hindrances?
On the basis of desire, on the basis of
ill will. Did I act out of those things?
So, okay, I didn't act out. Well, that's
good. And see, you recognize that. You You
And see, you recognize that. You You
knew that. You knew that you didn't act
out. But, if you don't stop and think
about it,
you will not necessarily become
self-aware of it.
That's why the Buddha encouraged in the
suttas uh people laypeople as well, by
the way.
It wasn't just the monks to to reflect
on their virtue, on their unbroken
virtue, cuz the gladness will come out
of it.
So, it's like, "Oh, yeah, I didn't I
didn't act out. I didn't break the
precepts." Yeah, but reflect on that as
well. Like, you're not doing it for yourself,
Like, you're not doing it for yourself,
you're doing it for the cheetah. You're
doing it for the animal, for the wild
animal. So,
So,
you ask yourself, "How did I spend my
day? How how um
How how um
what did I choose to attend to uh attend
to most of the time?
Did I act out of things? And then
recollect. Recollect, have have you Did
you act out? Did you say stuff? Did you
do stuff? And as you said, if not,
that's fine.
Then, okay, so did I think about things
that I shouldn't have? Did I choose to
revolve around
um
thoughts that aren't beneficial? How
often? How hard was it to say no?
How hard was it to say no?
And
you're doing all of this just to to shed
light onto your actions, onto your choices,
onto your actions, onto your choices,
uh and create that kind of
broader context that would then carry on
next day, because next day you know that
at the end of the day,
you will sit down
meticulously for an hour,
for an hour,
and you will be re-interrogating
yourself about the previous day.
So, when the next day comes,
when when you know, engaging with life
is sort of ongoing, and you have to do
this, do that,
you will not completely forget
before you choose, say, to engage with
hindrances or or or break the precepts.
You won't completely forget that, well,
at the end of the day, I will be asking
myself about this.
And that's how you you gradually sort of
increase the weight of that context, the
weight of those questions.
So that eventually
just the mere
uh remembrance of the fact that you will
be going through this self-interrogation
will be enough to like, "No, I won't
even do this."
It will highlight the choice
of choosing unwholesome.
Not saying no to desires when you should
have, and so on.
So
So that's that's how you can you can you
can actually meditate rightly, and you
could even make, say, a routine out of
it. And still not become like dry,
mindless, mechanical
technique kind of based sort of uh uh
and with a complete loss of any
self-awareness. Um because it's it's fundamentally it's
Um because it's it's fundamentally it's
choosing the skillful things and not
choosing unskillful things. It's what
comes to mind down.
It's what what results in samadhi, what
results in peace, what results in in in
pleasant abiding here and now.
Um and that's even when the Buddha was
talking to the to to lay people when he
said um they should frequently recollect the
um they should frequently recollect the
unbroken virtue, uh their faith in the
Buddha, Dharma, and the Sangha, meaning
basically reflecting along the lines of
Dharma. And that will provide pleasant abiding
And that will provide pleasant abiding
here and now for them in their household
lives. So
in the environment that's not
necessarily, you know, geared or or
oriented towards pleasant abiding here
and now
in in in terms of that peace.
So So yeah, like
you could just
and you don't even have to be asking the
same questions every time, but obviously
the whole point is
whichever way you to you were to
approach it, you know, different days,
different time, but
you approach it in regard to your
day, in regard to things that you've
been concretely doing
choosing, thinking about.
Not not in regard to like theoretical
aspects of the paticcasamuppada or
something. No, you want to be purifying your
No, you want to be purifying your
actions
and the way to do that is to start
shedding light on them retroactively,
acutely um even preemptively
and all of that comes out of like as I
said, investing the effort in um
first clarifying, then broadening those
contexts. So, in the end you wouldn't even
So, in the end you wouldn't even
necessarily have to ask yourself these
specific questions. It's enough just to
think about that
and all the right context would be
shedding the light, so to speak.
So, yeah. yeah.
Sit down
quietly, without disturbances, you know,
switch your phone off and stuff like
that. And uh And uh
just
a simple basic
self-reflection how did I spend my day?
How often did I engage with desire?
How often did I act out of ill will
by body
speech, by mind?
Was that beneficial or unbeneficial? How
does that make me feel now?
And uh and don't forget that you're not
seeking for the specific answers.
They will then make the problem go away.
You are shedding light.
That's all. That's all you're doing. So,
even if if you're unsure, hm I don't
know how does that make me feel and I
don't quite understand why that is
unwholesome or not. Doesn't matter. You
don't need to understand it there and
then. You don't need to find the answers
to it.
But the point is there you go. Through
asking questions, you have now
recognized that you don't understand the
extent of it. I don't understand to what extent
of it. I don't understand to what extent
saying no to desire is good. I don't
understand to what extent
um engaging with hindrances is bad. And
you recognize that. So you are
self-aware now
to certain extent of the
uh uh uh
lack of your understanding in regard to
certain things.
But if you never stop and thought about
those things, you would not you would
just carry on
um acting, choosing, thinking under the
impression that you already know these
things because at some point when you
read them, they made sense, you know?
They made sense, they reminded you of
something that you knew, you made the
connections in space and time, and now it's like,
in space and time, and now it's like,
"Oh yeah, I understand that." It's like,
"No, one thing is to like intellectually
have the
idea that represents it, and another
thing is to understand
as a result of which there there is no
craving or there is diminishing of
craving, diminishing of desire,
diminishing of wrong views, diminishing
of of dukkha.
Cuz that's what understanding is
measured about measured measured
through. Through the uh through the uh
Through the uh through the uh
diminishing and complete absence of
dukkha among amongst things that used to
cause it.
So
how did I spend my day?
How often did I engage with desire?
How often did I say no to it?
Was I successful or not overall?
Um
Did I choose things
that I knew
or maybe I didn't know, but they ended
up increasing the desire, increasing the
irritation, causing distraction? How
often did I do that?
Why did I do it? Why
why was I not able to say no? What
stopped me? What stopped me from
exercising the right choice there and
then? Uh and sit with that question even
Uh and sit with that question even
without answering it. Just
Seriously, what has stopped me
from exercising the right choice? I was
aware of it
and I still chose to go with it.
Where? Why?
Where did that pressure come from, so to
speak? Why Why did I have to go with it?
Why couldn't I say no?
And you know, different days you might
get different answers to the same
questions, but the point is
to to to make whole the whole thing
alive, so to speak. And you can do that
if the questions are not abstract, are
not dry, mechanical, mantra recitation.
If they pertain to things that you need
to think about, that you need to
recollect, that you need to bring up.
That you need to kind of
go through again.
Um and that's the point.
That's the right thinking. That's the
thinking that can actually
uh
be purified from the influences of lust,
of desire, of irritation, of distract-
distraction. And you could see if that thinking is is
And you could see if that thinking is is
sufficiently and regularly and uh
diligently developed on the basis of
making the right choices throughout the
day, on the basis of keeping the the the the
on the basis of keeping the the the the
virtue and the precepts and training in
those principles,
you could see how that thinking would be
quite uh quite pleasant, quite peaceful,
uh uh quite um imperturbable.
Because you're not afraid of your
thoughts anymore.
Because they have been purified from the
influxes of
uh those unskillful, unwholesome,
polluting choices that you have been
making only because you haven't shed
enough light on them. That's it. That's
it. So, that's your meditation, really.
So, that's your meditation, really.
Because every day you'll be doing stuff.
Every day you'll be choosing things.
Means every day you could be asking
yourself about it.
>> [clears throat]
>> And and and and broadening that whole
field of self-reflection.
Whereby the questions can
will eventually become subtler and and
more and more pertinent to the right
things. More acute, more accurate.
But it all comes through the through the
principle of the same practice.